*Music Plays*
I love the book of Ruth. I really do.
It's a simple story with a great many huge implications.
Ryan started it last week. We're in a small short series on it.
Today we're going to cover the rest of the first chapter,
but we're going to read the whole first chapter together, okay?
You don't have to read it out loud together. Just read along. I'll read it out loud for us.
So here we go.
"In the days when the judges ruled, there was a famine in the land.
And a man of Bethlehem and Judah went to sojourn in the country of Moab,
and he and his wife and his two sons.
The name of the man was Elimelech, the name of his wife Naomi,
and the names of their two sons were Malan and Chilion.
They were Ephrathites from Bethlehem and Judah.
They went to the country of Moab, and they remained there.
But Elimelech, the husband of Naomi, died, and she was left with her two sons.
These took Moabite wives.
The name of one was Orpah, the other was Ruth.
And they lived there about ten years.
And then both Malan and Chilion died.
So the woman was left without her two sons and her husband.
Then she arose with her daughters-in-law to return from the land of Moab,
because she'd heard that in the land of Moab that the Lord had visited his people
by giving them food.
So she departed from the place where she was and her two daughters-in-law with her,
and they went on the way to return to the land of Judah.
But Naomi said to her daughters-in-law, "Go, return each of you to your mother's house.
May the Lord deal kindly with you as you've dealt with the dead and with me.
May the Lord grant you that you may find a place of rest, each of you in the house of her husband."
And then she kissed him.
And they raised their voices, and they wept.
However, they said to her, "No, we will return with you to your people."
But Naomi said, "Return, my daughters. Why should you go with me?
Do I still have sons in my womb, that they would be your husbands?
Return, my daughters. For I'm too old to have a husband.
If I said I had hope, if I were even to have a husband tonight and give birth to sons,
would you therefore wait until they were grown?
Would you therefore refrain from marrying? No, my daughters.
It's much more bitter for me than for you,
because the hand of the Lord has come out against me."
And they raised up their voices, and they wept again.
And Orpah kissed her mother-in-law, but Ruth clung to her.
And then she said, "Behold, your sister-in-law has gone back to her people,
and her gods. Return after your sister-in-law."
But Ruth said, "Do not plead with me to leave you or turn back from following you.
Where you go, I'll go. Where you sleep, I will sleep.
Your people shall be my people, and your God, my God.
Where you die, there will I die, and there will I be buried.
May the Lord do so to me, and worse, if anything but death separates me from you."
And when she saw that she was determined to go with her, she stopped speaking to her about it.
So they went on until they came to Bethlehem.
And when they'd come to Bethlehem, all the city was stirred because of them.
And the women said, "Is this Naomi?"
But she said to them, "Do not call me Naomi. Call me Mara.
For the Almighty has dealt very bitterly with me.
I went away full, and the Lord has brought me back empty.
Why do you call me Naomi, since the Lord has testified against me, and the Almighty has afflicted me?"
And so it was, Naomi returned with her, Ruth the Moabitess, her daughter-in-law, who returned from the land of Moab.
And they came to Bethlehem at the beginning of the barley harvest."
All right.
So this is a simple story.
And it takes place at the time of the barley harvest.
When's that?
It's right now.
Barley is a winter grain, so you would harvest it right at the beginning of spring.
You would begin harvesting it.
So it's right at this part of the calendar year that the story that we just read is taking place.
It's when things look dead.
It's the story of a harvest after a hard winter.
When things look dead, but they're beginning to grow and blossom in the spring.
It's a story of life growing out of the ashes of suffering.
But today, we're just going to talk about the ashes of suffering.
Okay?
Because that's what this chapter is focused on.
We're going to look at the suffering.
So suffering.
I keep toying with the idea.
I should step out from behind the pulpit when I say this, right?
It's not gospel.
But I keep toying with the idea that in Scripture, all the books of poetry sort of function to emotionally connect with us during different times in our life as we go through suffering in different ways.
Proverbs in our youth when we're learning the rules.
Ecclesiastes for the younger adults in us that's asking what does it all mean.
Existential suffering there.
The song of Solomon for when we suffer in love.
Psalms is for that rough middle of our life when we're tossed about and we don't really know how to pray.
Job for the insuperable loss and despair as we sometimes encounter.
Lamentations for the incomprehensible tragedies that others built to visit upon us, right?
And we often think about Job as the book of suffering.
But each one of these deals with suffering in a way appropriate to different phases of our life.
And then we have Ruth, right?
Where we see suffering serving the function of helping us move back his direction.
And there's two options in which way we go.
Suffering is one of the main things that drives people to God, looking for ultimate answers.
It's also one of the main things that drives people away from God.
They start blaming and questioning.
Where's God?
And we see Naomi and Ruth kind of going different directions as they go through the same suffering together.
In chapter one.
To help us, I don't want to say this to compare.
They had it rough.
But I want to make sure that we can empathize with them and really understand what they're going through.
Because that's going to be important as we go through the rest of the book of Ruth, okay?
So, there's many types of physical suffering.
Actually, if you do any research, even if you just Google and look at AI's results,
you will see an enormous number of ways of cataloging suffering.
Mankind spends a lot of time trying to explain to ourselves how we're suffering and why we're suffering and what suffering means.
Because it's suffering.
We don't like it.
There's physical suffering, aging, pain, injury, illness.
There's psychological suffering, grief, loss, anxiety, fear, depression, guilt, shame.
Social suffering, isolation, injustice, conflict.
There's existential suffering.
Struggling with the meaning and purpose of what's going on around you, even in your suffering.
And suffering that begets more suffering.
From personal experience, I know that when you go through a suffering time, people pull back from you.
They don't want to be infected by it, right?
You have trouble.
You suffer.
People step away.
You feel isolated.
Maybe that's when you step into a pattern of addiction.
Make more bad choices.
Suffer more.
People step further away.
It's this cycle.
There's unfulfilled expectation, which is common in the West.
That's the West modern tragedy.
And it feels like that's nothing compared to real tragedy.
But we are suffering from it.
Don't undermine it, right?
Unfulfilled expectations.
That was the seventh betrayal.
That's the bottom level of hell, according to Dante.
That's as bad as it gets.
There's self-inflicted suffering.
The Greek tragedy.
There's the fallen world around us.
That's the tragedy in the Bible.
Many people call it acts of God.
They see it as divine discipline and suffering that refines us.
And that's clearly what Naomi's thinking here.
She thinks that she has been unfaithful, gone to Moab, and all this suffering has been visited upon her by a God who's disciplining her.
Right?
And she's bitter about it.
But the important thing to recognize is that all those things I just read that you go through, Naomi has experienced all of them.
All of them.
In the first five verses of this chapter.
Don't let it flow past you quickly just because it's quickly read.
Now, again, not for comparison, not to say she had it worse than us.
But you should be able to empathize with some of these things as we go through them.
In verse one, she's moving.
Right?
I know that some of you are moving right now.
It's really stressful.
You guys, you're telling me how stressful it is to move.
Right?
And she's, apart from anything else going on in her life, she had to move to a foreign country.
And at the end, she's moving back, dislocating her nest, as it were.
In psychology today, moving was listed as the number five most stressful thing behind, like, death and divorce.
Right?
So she's moving.
But this is more like moving out of a war zone.
Right?
She's moving because there's no food and her home has been torn up.
So it's an extra stressful moment.
In verse one, she's moving to an unfriendly foreign nation.
And to appreciate what that means, imagine that you have to leave Winchester because there's no food.
And the place you can find to go with food is, let's say, Iran.
It's a place where your ethnicity, your nationality and your religion are not welcome.
No one wants you there.
No one likes you there.
And you don't know anybody there.
There's no way to get on the grid there.
Right?
So that's what they've done.
They're doing that because of the political chaos.
The chapter starts with in the time of the judges.
The time of judges was a time when, if there was 40 years with no invasion and slaughter,
it was mentioned as a historical high point.
Right?
Every eight to 10 years, a new army would come through and ravage the countryside.
And take the food and run the people into caves.
And very likely this is where the famine came from.
Right?
We're told that these are people of Bethlehem.
Bethlehem, house of bread.
This was known from ancient times as a very fertile place with fertile soil.
So it was a target for invasions.
Right?
It's a place where they've moved because it seems like a great place to live.
But it's turned into chaos and they have to move to a foreign land where they're not welcome.
This is an incredible amount of suffering and we're still in verse one.
Okay?
Um, they have hunger.
They're in this place where they're not accepted and they have two sons.
Now, the language is a little ambiguous.
My best guess, and I could be wrong.
My best educated guess is that their sons were in the 12 to 14 range when they moved to Moab.
They were trying to move a place where their sons could have opportunity.
Right?
And that would mean 10 years later they would have been in the 22, 24 range.
Young adults when they would, when Naomi moved back.
Newly married.
So their newly married brides are still with Naomi.
So that's the time when you need a father.
These young men need to be set out to apprenticeship, to trade.
They need to learn how to deal with their hormones.
They need to know how to set up a household.
They need to know how to integrate with culture and be a man in the head of the house.
Naomi doesn't have a man.
Her husband died.
She doesn't have any uncles.
She doesn't have any grandfathers.
She's on her own in a foreign country where the customs are foreign.
And she's having to lead these young men through their teen years on her own.
That's a kind of suffering.
I've suffered staying here with people I know and having a couple of teenagers.
Right?
I can't even imagine doing it, you know, in a war torn zone and having to move to Iran, for lack of another comparative.
Her husband died.
And she had to direct her two sons into careers and marriages.
And they had to have weddings.
Weddings on that list of the things that are really stressful.
Just a good wedding.
Really stressful.
She had two weddings where the children chose women from a different faith and religion and stepped away from her.
This happens all the time with immigrant families.
Right?
You bring your child to a country for great opportunity and what you get is a loss of children who go into the culture and leave you.
And that's what she's experienced.
Her husbands took, I don't, it's a terrible choice.
They have to set up a household because, I don't know if you recognize this, but at the time, legal structures, you interacted with the law through the father's house that you lived in.
And you integrated with social structures through the father's household, the reputation of the father's household.
They don't have a father.
She needs one of her sons, Malon, to step up and become the head of household so that they can have access, they can get back on the grid.
Right?
How's he going to do that?
He has to have a family.
He has to have heirs.
He has to marry somebody.
It's a terrible choice, but he has to marry a Moabite woman.
Right?
And she can't be happy about that because, apart from anything else, Deuteronomy 7, one of the strict and all through the Torah, Israelite families are strictly prohibited from marrying with the small nations around them.
Specifically because they don't want those religions, the women pulling their children and the families away from worship of Yahweh.
Right?
That's why.
And that's exactly what Naomi sees happening.
And Moab, the main deity was Chemosh, and they have a cult of Moloch that everyone worshipped in, which was a cult of child sacrifice.
Right?
So she's moved into a culture and her sons are married into a culture where if things go wrong, if there's a famine, the proper thing to do may be to sacrifice your child.
There's a great picture of this, or not a great, but a terrifying picture of this in 2 Kings when the king of Moab sacrifices the crown prince on the walls of the city because he's afraid they're going to get overthrown.
Right?
And that's where they've moved.
Antithetical to the be fruitful and multiply teachings of the Old Testament.
So she has these Moabite wives that are pagan, and beyond that, Deuteronomy 23 strictly prohibits above and beyond all the others, a woman of Moabite shall not be allowed into the assembly.
Specifically because of child sacrifice.
Right?
And because of the fact that Moab showed themselves as an enemy to Israel and wouldn't let them into, they wouldn't feed them at one point in ancient history.
And this is this rift, which just made it that much more difficult.
Are you getting a feeling for the suffering of what Naomi's going through?
You've probably experienced some of these things in your life.
Imagine them all at once.
Right?
Her sons then, having married these pagan wives, died.
And she's left only with the two wives that she couldn't really have wanted to have in her family to begin with and that she's now not even really related to.
Right?
She knows nobody else in the country.
She's not connected to anybody else in the country except these two who, by the way, were married off to immigrant refugees.
So they probably weren't that special to their families.
Right?
It's not a pretty picture.
Her sons died.
We learned in verse 11, she's gone into menopause.
She can't have more children, which means she has no grandkids, no hope of getting them, no sons, no hope of getting more, no husband.
She has no father's household.
It's the equivalent of you having moved to Iran to escape, you know, a war-tongue famine.
You find yourself with no home, no friends, no cash, no ID.
You've lost your wallet.
You've lost your cell phone.
You can't get back on the grid.
There's nothing for you to do.
That's where she is.
That's what the first five verses are telling us.
So don't let that slip past you.
She's in desperate, desperate straits.
And she says the only thing for it is to go back to Israel and see if, or it's not Israel at the time, but go back to Bethlehem and see if things are better there.
Right?
This is suffering.
But the book of Ruth is about what's required for life to come out of the ashes of suffering.
Right?
And I'm just going to give you a sneak peek.
The answer is repentance.
It's Naomi turning around and returning faithfully to where she left behind, leaving the old life behind.
A committed turning is the answer.
So this is not just Naomi.
The nation is suffering.
It says in the time of Judges, this happened.
Naomi is the embodiment of the promise of the promised land that's starting to look like it'll fail.
Right?
God promised in this land of milk and honey, and they're getting invaded every so often.
Ruth is part of the story of Judges, although it's set apart from the tragic 12 and two stories in the book of Judges.
It's because this is the unexpected hand of God in the work of lives of those who are poor but faithful.
That's what we're about to see.
Faithful despite their suffering.
Judges, 1 Samuel, the first part of 1 Samuel and Ruth, are all set in the time of Judges.
And the larger narrative of those books shows us that the leadership and moral authority of Moses' family and the priesthood is failing.
Right?
They're not leading like they should.
They show us the corruption of the family of the first king of Israel, Saul, and how they committed themselves to military might and lost focus on God.
Right?
Um, the system of Judges is eroding and failing.
The famous quote multiple places in Judges is, "In those days there was no king in Israel, and every man did what was right in his own eyes."
That's what Elimelech and Naomi have done.
They did what was right in their own eyes for their kids.
They're going to give them a better opportunity instead of pursuing the promise given to them by God.
And unexpectedly out of the ashes and chaos, in Ruth we see the line of David arising.
That's bringing the nation to obedience, back to God, flourishing.
Giving them the promise that God gave to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob.
And Judges relied on their own judgment, just like Adam and Eve when they left Eden.
When they sought, David seeks to, he says, "God lead me in paths of righteousness for your namesake," famously.
Where does that come from?
We're told in Deuteronomy 7 and Exodus 20 that yeah, when you go away from my laws, the pain of that's going to be visited on a couple of generations.
It's not just going to affect you, it's going to affect your kids and grandkids.
But those who will be righteous and follow me faithfully, it'll be 10,000 years.
It'll just go on forever.
Thousands of generations will benefit from your decision.
And that's what we see happening here in this moment.
All of the nation and the house of the tribe and the city and this family is coming down to the lives of these two little women,
sitting at the nexus of history with all the weight of what's going wrong with the whole nation,
reflected in and resting upon the decisions they're about to make.
And the result of that is going to be the line of David and the fulfillment of the promise.
Okay?
So how they react in this moment of suffering is incredibly important beyond anything they could understand.
They would be shocked to know that we're standing here today talking about them.
Right?
All they know is that they've got no food and that their loved ones are dead.
This is the major, all of Israel in microcosm in these guys.
And it says in verse three, they were Ephratites of Bethlehem.
I said that Bethlehem means house of bread.
They came from a fertile place.
Ephratites.
Why is that thrown in there?
Why do they repeat?
They were from Bethlehem.
They were Ephratites from Bethlehem.
They repeated it because the patriarch of the country, Jacob, named Israel.
They were all sons of Jacob, sons of Israel.
His wife died when they got to the promised land and was buried in Ephratah.
And Ephratah, the ancient name of the place where Bethlehem is built, means fruitful
because the land had always been fruitful there.
But it doesn't actually mean fruitful.
The literal meaning of that word is ash heap.
Right?
So it's deep in the understanding of the Hebrew people that their patriarch seed, the promise,
is buried in the ash heaps of the country and they're waiting for it to spring forth and grow in Bethlehem.
And Naomi and Ruth are walking back to Bethlehem to see life grow out of the ashes if it can.
If they're faithful, will God make this tree grow?
God make this tree grow.
That's what the author is telling us.
Okay?
So Naomi's suffering, but it's important to recognize that Ruth is suffering too.
Are you guys loving to hear?
How many times have you heard the word suffering this morning?
As I said, Ruth is sufficiently unwanted by her family, it appears, that she was pawned off on starving immigrants, refugees who came into Moab.
So if you have a daughter, if you have a son, well, let's say you have a daughter.
You have a daughter and some starving refugees who don't know anybody and don't really have jobs come to Winchester.
What would it take for you to marry your daughter to that son, right?
Even if you're a loving, good guy, there's no future there, right?
It definitely means that Ruth didn't have better prospects.
So she doesn't maybe have a lot to go back to.
She doesn't have a great life before all of this befalls her in Naomi's household.
There's the inevitable friction with the mother-in-law of a foreign religion, right?
That's not going to have been fun.
And then, of course, there's the death of her husband and this quasi-homelessness that they're experiencing.
And what we have to understand is that things are bad for Ruth, but they're only going to get worse if she goes back to Bethlehem.
If she goes back to Bethlehem, she's now going to be in the condition that Naomi's currently in, of being in a foreign land where nobody wants her ethnicity.
She's not allowed in the assembly.
Everyone dislikes her because of her religion and her nation.
She's starting at a deficit in every conversation.
And she's not.
The only person she knows is this bitter, bitter, dispossessed old woman, right?
Her mother-in-law.
Let's just leave it at that.
Just if it was her mother-in-law, right?
I have to say, for the record, I love my mother-in-law.
She was great.
But if she goes to Israel, she's only going to know this bitter pauper with no future.
And things are going to be worse for her if she goes back.
Now, she will be leaving behind the culture of Chemesh and the cult of Molech and child sacrifice.
And these are all reasons for her to say, I would rather risk it all and leave this behind me and go follow Yahweh, right?
These are reasons to do that.
Another reason is she seems to like Naomi.
She doesn't want to leave this desperate old woman on her own, right?
She has a moment of kindness that springs up in her, it appears.
Now it's possible, I will say, so Ruth, she was a pagan, right?
She's stepping out of the cult of Molech when she makes this decision.
So it's possible that the reason she doesn't have kids is that they sacrifice their child.
If in your chest something rose up there in defense of her and say, that's not right, I want you to consider how you're thinking of the God of the Old Testament and the New Testament.
There's nothing in the text that says Ruth did that, okay?
I don't actually think she sacrificed her child.
But the heroes of the Old Testament were incestuous, murderers, liars, people who abused authority, adulterers, right?
They were people who lost out their own and killed others for their own benefit.
And one by one, God called them to repent for what they've done, turn around and come back and follow him.
And they did, and that's what made them people of God, right?
So if you think that Ruth was good as gold from the beginning and that's why God could use her,
if you think that the people in this room, the members of this church were righteous and then came to church and so God could use them, that's not right.
This is a congregation and Ruth was a people of repentance.
You have to have done the bad stuff to repent from it.
To repent is to turn and leave it behind, just burn those bridges and leave nothing behind and follow God.
But you can only do that when you feel the weight of your sin and walk away from it.
So Ruth is leaving behind a culture that was shocking and horrifying to the point that God had told his people don't even let them in the assembly, right?
There's all sorts of rules in Exodus about the foreigner being able to live with you but not the Moabites, right?
So that's where Ruth is coming from.
She's barren because she doesn't have a way to get a husband.
And the person that wrote, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us?
In the New Testament?
He was one who supported the murder and unjust punishment and torture of Christians.
He was a deep, deep sinner who understood that Christ had died for him long before he had repented of it.
And he repented and came back.
And also, don't kid yourself that these are ancient people who served idols and were urbane new people.
Modern people, right?
Quoting Tim Keller, who was quoting out Alexei de Tocqueville,
"The things which, if we lost, we would feel drawn to...
If we lost it, we would feel ourselves in deep despair."
That's an idol.
That's the definition of an idol.
It's an incomplete joy of this world that we've built our lives upon
and irrationally expected fulfillment and abundance to come through.
That's what they were doing.
They thought if they followed Chemosh and Molech and sacrificed their children,
they would get good stuff out of it.
Right?
They were irrationally attached to this, thinking it would bring them good.
And anything that we...any incomplete joy of this world that we build our life on
and expect fulfillment and abundance through,
any of these things which absorb our heart and our imagination more than God,
anything we seek to give you, that you seek to give you what only God can give you,
those are idols, just as real and which we follow just as fervently as all the ancient pagans
that we read about and look at askance in the Old Testament.
Right?
Naomi actually, you could say, was guilty of an idolatry.
She seemed to have put the idea of prospering ahead of service to God.
They wanted to go to Moab.
They were more worried about the good of their children, the future prospects and food,
than they were sticking it out within the way God had told them.
I've been reading Gulag Archipelago lately.
It's a 2,000 page catalog of horrors that man visits on man.
Right?
It's very long.
There was, in the Soviet Union, it was an experiment to try to get rid of greed,
try to get rid of inequity, try to get rid of the things that caused hunger and disparity.
And the result was massive injustice, the internment of people in horrible conditions.
And it's just recorded for 2,000 pages in Gulag Archipelago.
Alexander Solzhenitsyn, at the end of that time, who was a good communist, who found, saw where it led.
He wrote, "The meaning of earthly existence lies not as we've grown used to thinking and prospering,
but in the development of our souls."
That's what they came to after that giant failed experiment.
You can't put prospering as your idol.
As C.S. Lewis says, "If we find within ourselves a desire that nothing in this world can satisfy,
the most probable explanation is that we're made for another world.
Probably, earthly pleasures were never meant to satisfy,
but only to arouse, to suggest the real thing."
All that we call human history, money, poverty, ambition, war, prostitution, classes, empire, slavery,
all that Naomi's going through is the long terrible story of man trying to find something other than God which can make him happy.
So we have two women going through this kind of suffering.
And they're going different directions.
One had the option to pursue righteous, but she did what was right in her own eyes.
Now they have the option to either blame God or claim God as their own.
And the role that we see God playing in our suffering will dramatically affect how we experience hardship.
And Ruth is inadvertently going to lead Naomi into a better way of experiencing hardship.
Just through simple faithfulness.
So let's walk through the new passage in Ruth 1:6-22.
Ruth and Naomi, it says that they have, in verse 6,
"She arose with their daughters-in-law and returned from the land of Moab
because she'd heard in the land of Moab that the Lord had visited his people by giving them food."
Right?
"There's food, safe to go back."
"It's a three to four day walk from what's modern Joban Jordan to Bethlehem."
So, two paupered, impoverished women on their own walking for four days.
That's suffering by itself.
Right?
And that's what they're doing.
They're walking back.
And I imagine in my mind when they get to the border between the countries,
there's a little rise and Naomi stops and says to her daughters-in-law,
"Okay, time to go back."
Right?
"I'm doing this on my own.
We are no longer one but two groups of people."
Right?
And in this passage, there are four characters, but there's really three.
Orpah is just a passing character that stands in contrast to Ruth, okay?
The names that are mentioned frequently are Naomi, Ruth, and the Lord.
These are the three characters that the author is showing us how they relate to each other.
And if you don't know this, parenthetical, in your Bible when it says Lord, L-O-R-D, and it's all normal cases,
that just means someone who rules a piece of land, the local king or ruler, potentate.
He's the Lord of the area.
But if it's Lord, L, capital O-R-D, all uppercase, drop case,
that's the author, the translator's effort to carry on the tradition of showing reverence by not writing the name of God.
In the Old Testament, they would use four letters that sound like Yahweh when you say it out loud.
We say Yahweh, breath of God, Yahweh.
And they would use that as a placeholder.
And everybody knew that meant God, but they didn't want to say his name out of reverence.
In the New Testament, I'm sorry, in our Bibles today, it says L-O-R-D, all uppercase.
And that means name of God, okay?
So the name of God is referenced seven times and nine times, they call him the Almighty twice.
The most referenced person in this chapter, okay?
So they're talking about how Naomi and Ruth relate to Yahweh.
In 613, this whole section, it's just a litany of bitterness that Naomi's saying how God is judging her and has made her life bitter.
I think she recognizes, rightly or wrongly, that this is being visited on her because of her unfaithfulness, but she's not bending her neck to it.
She just feels like she's been ruined.
Her life is over, right?
She says in the end, don't call me Naomi, which means sweet, call me pleasant, call me Mara, which means bitter.
There's nothing less but this husk of bitterness in verse 20.
And she feels judged, and she feels unloved.
She's had everything we've talked about this morning, all that suffering on her shoulders, and she believes she brought it on herself.
And God is judging her because of all the stuff she did, and there's nothing she can do about it in her life as an ash heap.
And that's where Naomi is.
So, she tells her daughters to leave her three times.
The first time, in verse 8 and 9, she says, "I'm not your mother."
We talked about how important it was to have a father's house at the time, but it was also true that a widowed daughter would go back to the apartments of her mother in their home.
And her mother would help her through the grieving process, help her get rehabilitated, reintroduce her to the community, help her get ready to go out there, find another man, build another house.
That's the way it worked.
So, it was important that your mother take care of you and rehabilitate you in the house of your father.
And Naomi, instead of going back to the house of your father, she calls out their mother, right?
Go back to your mother's house.
I'm not your mother.
I can't do that stuff for you, right?
That's what she's saying.
And they respond to that.
She says, "And may Yahweh give you what he didn't give me," right?
In verse 9, "May he give you kindness and rest and husbands."
If you come with me, I can't give you those things.
He might give it to you.
They respond to her with the language of otherness.
"Oh no, let we want to come with you and your people," right?
So, this divide is there.
Verse 2 then, after they've cried and said, "No, we don't want to leave you."
She makes it more clear, "Not do you need to go back to your mother, but there is no future if you stay with me."
Explicit description of how they will only suffer if they come with her, she says.
In menopause, in verse 11, her life and purpose, they've just passed her by.
I spoke at a church recently which was struggling and they, I said, essentially, you know, "Well, what's your vision for the future?"
And they said, "We had our vision, it didn't work," right?
And they're just depressed.
This church went through that but came out the other side.
We've seen the regrowth.
It's difficult to get past your suffering and on to growth.
How do you do that?
You change your direction and hopefully you have somebody like Ruth in your life, right?
In verse 13, she says, "Don't kid yourself.
The feelings of affection you have for me aren't going to last," right?
"Are you really going to go all that time without having another husband just because you like me?"
"Are you really going to stay outside of culture and unattached?"
"No, you're not going to do that.
You're going to want to have sons.
Don't kid yourself."
And in verse 13, she says explicitly, "Yahweh is against me.
If you come with me, he's going to be against you too," is the implication, right?
"You don't want to be with me."
At which point, in verse 9, she had kissed them goodbye and they had not reciprocated.
They'd say, "No, no, we don't want to leave you."
At this point, Orpah says, "Yeah, you're right," and kisses her, which was the rational thing to do, right?
It made sense.
Orpah's like, "Yeah, I do want a husband.
Yeah, you are cursed.
Yeah, this is going badly.
It's been nice knowing you.
I'm really going to miss you.
I'm going to go back to my mother's house and hope it gets better," right?
"It's only going to get worse if we go to Israel."
That was the reasonable thing to do if you're pursuing good things, if you're pursuing a material life, prosperity.
It's the only choice.
Ruth, apparently, was not pursuing prosperity.
So, instead of weeping and leaving, she clings to her and does the unreasonable thing.
In verse 15, perhaps now frustrated because this crying girl is holding on to her instead of walking away like it was a reasonable thing to do, like she's been told to do multiple times, Naomi gets succinct and to the point.
She says, "Your sister-in-law has gone back to her people and to her gods.
You are not like me.
Go back to your gods.
You know there's a difference between us."
And that seemed to be the point that set Ruth off, right?
She didn't appreciate that.
This is the pivot point in the story of Ruth, is that moment when Naomi says, "Go back to your gods."
Ruth has this eloquent outburst that we still quote today, frequently out of context, but it's a beautiful statement, right?
Don't plead with me to turn my back.
Where you go, I'll go.
Where you sleep, I'll sleep.
Your people shall be my people.
Your God, my God.
Where you die, I'll die, and there will I be buried.
This says, "May the Lord do to me so and worse, if anything but death separates you from me."
Most scholars think she made some sort of sign, "May the Lord do so to me, cut me off."
I tend to think that she'd been paying attention and listening to Naomi's subtext.
Naomi has been quite justifiably complaining about all the stuff God's done to her because of her unfaithfulness when she left Bethlehem.
And Ruth is saying, "If I'm unfaithful to you and leave like you did, may the Lord do to me everything you said he's doing to you and worse."
If I leave you.
I'm not leaving you, old woman.
Right?
And I love the uncomfortable car ride.
When she saw that she was determined to go with her, she just stopped speaking to her about it.
Right?
She didn't agree.
She just said, "Ugh."
And they had this quiet walk the rest of the way of Bethlehem.
That's what it sounds like.
Because, Ruth's just not leaving.
It doesn't make sense.
Naomi's not ready to accept that.
But she desperately needs it.
Right?
This was a public declaration of a private determination to change the direction of her life and commit to it.
She's leaving Chemosh and Moloch behind.
So in this moment of decision, this is what sets up the rest of the book.
It's a moment of unnecessary kindness, but Ruth just won't leave her.
And it not only changes the course of Naomi's life, but it changes the course of the family's life and of the city's life and the town of Bethlehem and the nation of Israel through her descendant David.
And it's led us to being here today through Christ, whose fulfillment of the prophecy of the kingdom of God growing out of the stump of David.
Because of the choice Ruth makes now and the choice Boaz is going to make in a few chapters.
But I don't think it changed Ruth.
Right?
I think that change had already happened.
That's why she got frustrated when they said, "You're God."
She's like, "It's not my God."
Right?
She cements it in place when she's forced to declare an allegiance.
And she opts to push forward with simple,
practical, faithful acts of righteousness day after day trying to help this old woman not starve.
She's looking out for the widowed and the dispossessed.
She's not trying to change history.
Sorry, the widowed and the dispossessed.
Even though she herself is now widowed and dispossessed by the effort.
Right?
She's just so committed to leaving the child sacrifice behind.
She's burning all her bridges and saying, "I'm going to repent.
Whatever God does for us is what's going to happen."
And I think that's what it feels like to really repent.
We have the sinner's prayer, "Dear God, come into my life, I want to follow you."
Those are important words.
And what's behind it is an existing decision that you're leaving your old life behind.
Burning it.
You're dead to it.
And you're moving a new direction.
In the midst of our great suffering, what's required for life to spring out of ashes?
Yielding our will to God.
To be dead to our old life.
Swearing allegiance to His righteousness.
And letting it inform our small daily actions like Ruth.
We cannot see, Ruth could not see the impact.
But God can use us, even in the midst of our suffering, to profoundly impact the world and the people around us.
And He will.
Even though you probably won't see it.
So faithfulness is so much greater than the ashes of Ephratah, right?
Ephratah, life coming from the ashes.
When you die to self.
It's what Christ talks about in the passage we read this morning from John 12.
Unless a grain of wheat falls into the earth and dies, it remains alone.
But if it dies, Ruth said, I'm dead to my old life, right?
It's so far, it's something I cannot achieve again.
She hated her life.
She was no longer loyal to it.
She loved the life of Christ, the life of God.
It dies, it bears much fruit.
Whoever loves his life will lose it.
Whoever hates his life in this world will keep it for eternal life.
Hating your life and loving your life, those are words of loyalty.
I'm going to cling to the new, Naomi.
I'm going to hate the old.
I'm just going to burn the bridges and not even go back and see my mother again.
That's what Ruth did.
This is not a lottery.
You're not throwing it out there to see if it works.
It's a determination, a desperate, solid hope that you're going to follow and burn the ships and the bridges behind you.
Ruth became dead to her old life and she clung energetically, almost irrationally, to her new life with Naomi and Yahweh, which were the characters in our story.
This is the model of repentance.
She burned her bridges.
She energetically committed herself to this new life in whatever form it might take.
She couldn't possibly have thought that it would be a prosperity.
But she didn't toy around.
She committed.
You have to not toy around.
You have to turn from your old ways, pursue God.
The God who has this book will go on to show us, will give you the strength and the means required to do so.
To pursue his righteousness far beyond what you can imagine.
That's the lesson of suffering in Ruth.
I'm going to say a benediction here this morning.
And then some people are going to come up.
And if you want to come and talk to somebody or pray with someone about repentance, about following God in a committed way, we'd love to talk to you, okay?
So I'm going to pray.
And then if you guys can, you know, quietly go out and get your kids, find good lunch.
And those who want to stay and pray with us, we welcome it.
Father God, thank you for the story of Ruth.
Thank you for people like her in our history that make your righteousness available to us down to thousands of generations.
We pray that you would bless our efforts to follow you.
Give us the strength when we have no strength.
Let us leave behind the things that we just habitually follow like our own prosperity.
Let us grow in our affection for you and our loyalty and our faithfulness to you, Lord.
Give us people in our lives that will support that.
Let this church become a community that provides that support to others.
Thank you in Jesus' name.
You guys go with God and have a great week.
We're going to be here.